Nicholas Low Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Nicholas Low Papers 1773-1897 (bulk 1784-1828)
MSS30627
Low, Nicholas, 1739-1826
36,000 items
100 containers plus 4 oversize
40 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
New York merchant, financier, land speculator, and state legislator. Family and business correspondence, business and ship's papers, legal papers, accounts of voyages to Asia, Europe, and South America, and printed matter. Includes correspondence with foreign merchants and relates to trade conditions, Loyalist matters, and to events in Congress during the first session following the adoption of the Constitution.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Low, Isaac, 1735-1791--Correspondence.; Low, Isaac--Correspondence.; Low, Nicholas, 1739-1826.
Organizations
Great Britain. Army--Officers.; Low & Wallace (New York, N.Y.); Mordecai Lewis & Company (Philadelphia, Pa.)--Correspondence.; Society for Establishing Useful Manufactures.; United States. Congress.; United States. Constitution.
Subjects
American loyalists.; Business records--New York (State); Commerce.; Land speculation--Kentucky.; Land speculation--New York (State); Land speculation--Ohio.; Merchants--New York (State)--New York.; Merchants--Pennsylvania--Philadelphia.; Ship's papers--18th century.; Ship's papers--19th century.; Voyages and travels.
Places
Argentina--Commerce.; Asia--Description and travel.; Ballston Spa (N.Y.)--History.; Canada--Commerce.; China--Commerce.; Europe--Commerce.; Europe--Description and travel.; Great Britain--Commerce.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--United States.; India--Commerce.; Ireland--Commerce.; Lowville (N.Y.)--History.; Mexico--Commerce.; New York (State)--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.; New York (State)--Social life and customs.; South America--Description and travel.; United States--Commerce.; United States--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783--Claims.; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783.; United States--Politics and government--1783-1789.; Uruguay--Commerce.; West Indies--Commerce.
Occupations
Land speculators.; Merchants.
Provenance
The papers of Nicholas Low, New York merchant, financier, land speculator, and state legislator, were given to the Library of Congress by Emil Hurja in 1938-1939.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Nicholas Low are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1739, Mar. 30 Born near New Brunswick, N.J.
1784 Appointed member of the committee to receive subscription for the stock in the Bank of New York
1785 Elected a director of the Bank of New York
1788 Elected on the Federalist slate to the New York state convention that met at Poughkeepsie, N.Y., and ratified the United States Constitution
1793 Gave support to the Society for Establishing Useful Manufactures, Paterson, N.J.
1796 Became a part proprietor of a large tract of land in Jefferson and Lewis counties, New York, beginning his career as a land speculator
1810 Built a hotel and a cotton factory, Ballston, N.Y.
1814 Joined the New York Hussars to defend New York, N.Y., against the British
1826, Nov. 15 Died, New York
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Nicholas Low (1739-1826) span the years 1773-1897, with the bulk of the material from 1784 to 1828. The collection consists largely of financial papers and correspondence and includes family and business correspondence of Low & Wallace, New York, New York, ship records, legal records, accounts of voyages to Asia, Europe, and South America, and printed matter. Included are correspondence with foreign merchants, letters from Low’s brother, Isaac Low (1735-1791), and his nephew, Isaac Low (commissary-general, British army), dealing with trade conditions, Loyalist matters, progress of British-American relations, and the proceedings for recovery of property seized from Isaac Low during the Revolution. Correspondence of Mordecai Lewis & Company, merchants of Philadelphia, relates in part to events in Congress during the first session following the adoption of the Constitution. The collection also includes papers relating to Low’s lands in Kentucky, Ohio, and New York; the founding of Ballston Spa and Lowville, New York; the Society for Establishing Useful Manufactures; and other matters relating to life in New York. Prominent as well is material relating to commercial contacts abroad, mainly in Britain, Ireland, and the European continent, with connections also in Argentina, Canada, China, India, Mexico, the West Indies, and Uruguay.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is organized into family papers, general correspondence, special correspondence, miscellany, and oversize material. The family papers and special correspondence in this collection are arranged alphabetically by name of person or institution. The general correspondence is organized chronologically and therein by name of city.
Container List
- Family papers (Box 1)
  - Allen, John (Box 1)
  - Low, Alice (Box 1)
  - Low, Catherine (Box 1)
  - Low, Cornelius (Box 1)
  - Low, Elizabeth (Box 1)
  - Low, Henrietta (Box 1)
  - Low, Isaac (1783-1818) (brother) (Box 1)
  - Low, Isaac 1784-1803 (nephew) (Box 1)
  - Ogden, Euphemia (Box 2)
  - Ogden, Samuel (Box 2)
  - Wallace, Alexander, 1785-1798 (Box 2)
  - Wallace, Cornelius Low (Box 2)
  - Wallace, Gertrude (Box 2)
  - Wallace, Hugh (Box 2)
  - Wallace, Magil (Box 2)
  - Wallace, Sarah (Box 2)
  - Wallace, William (Box 2)
- General correspondence (Box 3)
  - 1773 (Box 3)
  - 1777-1778 (Box 3)
  - 1777 (Box 3)
    - Glasgow, Scotland-London, England (Box 3)
    - Swansea, Mass.-Philadelphia, Pa. (Box 3)
  - 1781, Curacao (Box 3)
  - 1782 (Box 3)
  - 1783 (Box 3)
    - Ostend, Belgium-Moudon, Switzerland (Box 3)
    - Cheshire, Conn.-St. Thomas, V. I. (Box 3)
  - 1784 (Box 4)
    - Bay Honduras-Newry, Ireland (Box 4)
    - Kingston, Jamaica-Cadiz, Spain (Box 5)
    - Green Bush, Maine-Philadelphia, Pa. (Box 5)
    - Philadelphia, Pa.-Williamsburg, Va. (Box 6)
  - 1785 (Box 7)
    - Anvers, Belgium-St. Eustatius, D.W.I. (Box 7)
    - Derby, England-Cadiz, Spain (Box 7)
    - Savannah, Ga.-Spotswood, N.J. (Box 7)
    - Albany, N.Y.-Tortola, V.I. (Box 8)
  - 1786 (Box 9)
    - Anveis, Belgium-Cadiz, Spain (Box 9)
    - Hartford, Conn.-Schenectady, N.Y. (Box 9)
    - Philadelphia, Pa.-St. Croix, V I. (Box 10)
  - 1787 (Box 10)
    - Dominico, B.W.I.-Londonderry, Ireland (Box 10)
    - Lisbon, Portugal-Trinidad (Box 11)
    - Sandy Hook, Conn.-St. Croix, V.I. (Box 11)
  - 1788 (Box 12)
    - Rum Cay, Bahama Islands-Trinidad (Box 12)
    - Augusta, Ga.-St. Croix, V.I. (Box 12)
  - 1789 (Box 13)
    - Rio Essoquibo, Br. Guiana-Lamberton, Scotland (Box 13)
    - Millstone, Conn.-Philadelphia, Pa. (Box 13)
    - Philadelphia, Pa.-Providence, R. I. (Box 14)
  - 1790 (Box 14)
    - Rio Essequibo, Br. Guiana-Teneriffe, Spain (Box 14)
    - New Haven, Conn.-Green Bush, Mass. (Box 14)
    - Burlington, N. J.-St. Croix, V.I. (Box 15)
  - 1791 (Box 16)
    - Liverpool, England-Gibralter, Spain (Box 16)
    - Canaan, Conn.-Philadelphia, Pa. (Box 16)
    - Philadelphia, Pa.-Richmond, Va. (Box 17)
  - 1792 (Box 18)
    - China-Gibralter, Spain (Box 18)
    - Hamburg, Conn.-Ballston, N. Y. (Box 18)
    - Catskill, N.Y.-Richmond, Va. (Box 19)
  - 1793 (Box 19)
    - Curacao, D. Antilles-London, England (Box 19)
    - Flanders, France-Gibralter, Spain (Box 20)
    - Hartford, Conn.-Richmond, Va. (Box 20)
  - 1794 (Box 21)
    - Falmouth, England-Berne, Switzerland (Box 21)
    - Millstone, Conn.-Richmond, Va. (Box 21)
  - 1795 (Box 22)
    - Liverpool, England-Lausanne, Switzerland (Box 22)
    - Hamburg, Conn.-Richmond, Va. (Box 22)
  - 1796 (Box 23)
    - Falmouth, England-Madeira, Portugal (Box 23)
    - Hartford, Conn.-Pittsfield, Vermont (Box 23)
  - 1797 (Box 24)
    - London, England-Lausanne, Switzerland (Box 24)
    - Hamburg, Conn.-Philadelphia, Pa. (Box 24)
  - 1798 (Box 25)
    - London, England-Kingston, Jamaica (Box 25)
    - Middletown, Conn.-Richmond, Va. (Box 25)
  - 1799 (Box 26)
    - Falmouth, England-Leghorn, Italy (Box 26)
    - Hartford, Conn.-St. Croix, V.I. (Box 26)
  - 1800 (Box 27)
    - Falmouth, England-Cadiz, Spain (Box 27)
    - Hamburg, Conn.-Richmond, Va. (Box 27)
  - 1801 (Box 28)
    - St. Petersburg-Strabane, Ireland. (Box 28)
    - Lexington, Ky.-Richmond, Va (Box 28)
  - 1802 (Box 29)
    - St. Petersburg-Fully, Switzerland (Box 29)
    - Plainfield, Conn.-Philadelphia, Pa. (Box 29)
  - 1803 (Box 30)
    - St. Pierre-Madeira, Portugal (Box 30)
    - Hartford, Conn.-Richmond, Va. (Box 30)
  - 1804 (Box 31)
    - Liverpool, England-Fully, Switzerland (Box 31)
    - Hartford, Conn.-St. Croix, V.I. (Box 31)
  - 1805 (Box 32)
    - Buenos Aires, Spain (Box 32)
    - Montevideo, Spain (Box 32)
    - Hartford, Conn.-Richmond, Va. (Box 33)
  - 1806 (Box 34)
    - Montreal, Canada-Larned, Ireland (Box 34)
    - Londonderry, Ireland-Fully, Switzerland (Box 35)
    - Litchfield, Conn.-Geneva, N. Y. (Box 35)
    - Lansingburgh, N.Y.-Monkton, Vt. (Box 36)
  - 1807 (Box 37)
    - St. Georges, Bermuda (Box 37)
    - Montevideo, Spain (Box 37)
    - Canton, China-Junior, W. Va. (Box 38)
  - 1808 (Box 39)
    - Montreal, Canada-Madeira, Portugal (Box 39)
    - New London, Conn.-Perth Amboy, N. J. (Box 39)
    - Albany, N. Y.-Norfolk, Va. (Box 40)
  - 1809 (Box 41)
    - London, England. (Box 41)
    - Lisbon, Conn.-Philadelphia, Pa. (Box 41)
  - 1810 (Box 41)
    - Liverpool, England-Trinidad (Box 41)
    - Lisbon, Conn.-Canandaigua, N.Y. (Box 41)
    - Claverack, N.Y.-Philadelphia, Pa. (Box 42)
  - 1811 (Box 42)
    - London, England-Trinidad (Box 42)
    - Lisbon, Conn.-Utica, N. Y. (Box 42)
  - 1812 (Box 42)
    - London, England-Trinidad (Box 42)
    - Lisbon, Conn.-Philadelphia, Pa (Box 42)
  - 1813 (Box 43)
    - London, England-Elmwood, Ont. (Box 43)
    - Caldwell, N.J.-Philadelphia, Pa. (Box 43)
  - 1814 (Box 43)
    - St. Vincent, B.W.I.-Trinidad (Box 43)
    - Lisbon, Conn.-Philadelphia, Pa. (Box 43)
  - 1815 (Box 44)
    - London, England-Rotterdam, Holland (Box 44)
    - Hadley, Mass.-Philadelphia, Pa. (Box 44)
  - 1816 (Box 44)
    - London, England-Gibraltar, Spain (Box 44)
    - New Brunswick, N.J.-Philadelphia, Pa. (Box 44)
  - 1817 (Box 45)
    - London, England-Trinidad (Box 45)
    - Lebanon, N.J.-Philadelphia, Pa. (Box 45)
  - 1818 (Box 45)
    - London, England (Box 45)
    - Lisbon, Conn.-Alexandria, Va. (Box 45)
  - 1819 (Box 46)
    - London, England (Box 46)
    - Lisbon, Conn.-Philadelphia, Pa. (Box 46)
  - 1820 (Box 46)
    - London, England (Box 46)
    - Albany, N.Y.-Philadelphia, Pa. (Box 46)
  - 1821 (Box 46)
    - London, England (Box 46)
    - Perth Amboy, N.J.-Winchester, N.Y. (Box 46)
  - 1822 (Box 47)
    - London, England (Box 47)
    - New Haven, Conn.-Waddington, N. Y. (Box 47)
  - 1823, Albany, N.Y.-Winchester, N.Y. (Box 47)
  - 1824, Albany, N.Y.-Waddington, N. Y. 48 (Box 47)
  - 1825 (Box 48)
    - London, England (Box 48)
    - Caldwell, N.J.-Utica, N.Y. (Box 48)
  - 1826 (Box 48)
    - Paris, France (Box 48)
    - Greenfield, Mass.-Watertown, N.Y. (Box 48)
  - 1827 (Box 48)
    - London, England (Box 48)
    - Albany, N.Y.-Watertown, N.Y. (Box 48)
  - 1828 (Box 49)
    - London, England-Paris, France (Box 49)
    - Albany, N. Y.-Watertown, N.Y. (Box 49)
  - 1829 (Box 49)
    - London, England-Paris, France (Box 49)
    - Albany, N. Y.-Winchester, N.Y. (Box 49)
  - 1830 (Box 50)
    - London, England-Paris, France (Box 50)
    - Albany, N. Y.-LeRoysville, Pa. (Box 50)
  - 1831 (Box 50)
    - London, England-Paris, France (Box 50)
    - Albany, N.Y.-Woodburn, N.Y. (Box 50)
  - 1832, Hudson, N.Y. (Box 50)
  - 1833, Hudson, N.Y.-New York (Box 50)
  - 1834 (Box 50)
    - London, England (Box 50)
    - Hudson, N.Y. (Box 50)
  - 1835 (Box 50)
    - London, England (Box 50)
    - Ballston, N.Y.-Waddington, N.Y. (Box 50)
  - 1836 (Box 51)
    - London, England (Box 51)
    - Albany, N.Y.-Utica, N.Y. (Box 51)
  - 1837 (Box 51)
    - London, England-Madeira, Portugal (Box 51)
    - Bath, N.Y.-Painted Post, N.Y. (Box 51)
  - 1838 (Box 51)
    - London, England (Box 51)
    - St. Mary’s County, Md.-New York (Box 51)
  - 1839 (Box 51)
    - London, England (Box 51)
    - Boston, Mass.-Bellows Falls, Vt. (Box 52)
  - 1840, Albany, N.Y.-Utica, N.Y. (Box 52)
  - 1841, Ballston, N.Y.-Stockholm, N.Y. (Box 52)
  - 1842, Bath, N.Y.-Utica, N. Y (Box 52)
  - 1843, Bath, N.Y.-Lowville, N.Y. (Box 52)
  - 1844, Oswego, N.Y. (Box 52)
  - 1845, Albany, N.Y. (Box 52)
  - 1847, Bath, N.Y. (Box 52)
  - 1848, Ballston, N.Y.-Schenectady, N.Y. (Box 52)
  - 1849, Bath, N.Y.-Utica, N.Y. (Box 52)
  - 1850, Bath, N.Y.-New York (Box 52)
  - 1851, Bath, N.Y. (Box 52)
  - 1852, Lowville, N.Y. (Box 52)
  - 1853, Brasher, N.Y. (Box 52)
  - 1854, Brasher, N.Y.-Lowville, N.Y. (Box 52)
  - 1855 (Box 52)
    - London, England (Box 52)
    - Brasher, N.Y.-New York (Box 52)
  - 1856, Utica, N.Y. (Box 52)
  - 1858, Bath, N.Y.-Minerva, N. Y. (Box 52)
  - 1859, Bath, N.Y. (Box 52)
  - 1860, Bath, N.Y.-Prattsburg, N.Y. (Box 52)
  - 1861, Bath, N.Y. (Box 52)
  - 1862, Brasher, N.Y. (Box 52)
  - 1863, Bath, N.Y. (Box 52)
  - 1864, Brasher, N.Y.-Lowville, N.Y. (Box 52)
  - 1867 (Box 52)
  - 1869, New York-Washington, D.C. (Box 52)
  - 1874-1875 (Box 52)
  - 1890, Red Bank, N.J.-Brooklyn, N.Y. (Box 53)
  - 1894, New York (Box 53)
  - 1895 (Box 53)
  - 1896 (Box 53)
  - 1897, New York (Box 53)
  - Undated (Box 53)
- Special correspondence (Box 54)
  - Bank of New York (Box 54)
  - Bank of Pennsylvania (Box 54)
  - Bank of the United States (Box 54)
  - Bank of Utica (Box 54)
  - Slave miscellany (Box 54)
- Miscellany (Box 55-100)
  - Accounts, invoices, legal matter, etc. (formerly listed as nos. 127-172) See also Oversize (Box 55-99)
  - Items re Society for Establishing Useful Manufactures (formerly no. 173) (Box 100)
- Oversize (Box OV 1-OV 4)
  - Accounts (removed from Containers 55-100) (Box OV 1-OV 4)